47% of people using Claude only ever ask once,
使用Claude的人中有47%只问一次，
get an answer and close the tab.
得到答案后就关闭了标签页。
You probably feel it.
你可能有这种感觉。
You type something in and get something back
你输入一些内容，得到一些回复，
and it's almost what you needed, but not quite.
几乎是你需要的，但又不完全对。
And you are not sure why.
你不确定原因是什么。
The tutorials don't really help.
教程并没有真正帮助。
The prompting tips don't stick.
提示技巧没有记住。
And the gap between what AI can actually do
AI实际能做的和你能得到的之间的差距，
and what you can actually get out of it, just see there.
你可以看到。
And the gap has a name.
这个差距有个名字。
Today, we are going to close the gap.
今天，我们要缩小这个差距。
The 47% isn't a failure of the technology,
47%并不是技术的失败，
is the absence of framework.
而是缺乏框架。
92% of students now use the AI regularly.
现在92%的学生定期使用AI。
Adoption isn't a question anymore,
采用不再是一个问题，
but adoption is not fluency.
但采用并不等于流利。
And the most people have never been clearly shown
而大多数人从未清楚地看到
what the difference between them actually looks like.
它们之间的区别是什么样的。
The question is no longer why the people are using AI.
问题不再是人们为什么使用AI。
The question is, are they using it well?
问题是，他们是否使用得当？
Right now, most people fall into one of two patterns.
现在，大多数人落入两种模式之一。
They're either overwhelmed,
他们要么感到不知所措，
drowning in tools, prompts, and possibilities,
淹没在工具、提示和可能性中，
not knowing where to start,
不知道从哪里开始，
or they're overconfident, taking AI outputs at face value,
要么他们过于自信，直接接受AI的输出，
not knowing what to question,
不知道该质疑什么，
producing work that looks right, but isn't.
产生看起来正确但实际上不对的作品。
Both patterns lead to the same place.
这两种模式都导致同样的结果。
Mediocre results and enormous missed potential.
平庸的结果和巨大的潜在机会被错失。
There is a third way.
That third way has a name,
and it was developed by some of the world's leading thinkers
on human AI interaction.
It's called AI fluency.
Anthropica partner with Professor Joseph Faller
from University College Cork
and Professor Rick Dutkin from Ringling College
to create a rigorous, accessible framework
for working with AI well.
They define AI fluency as the ability
to work with AI systems in ways that are effective,
efficient, ethical, and safe.
Four words, but they represent a completely different
relationship with AI than most people have today.
Here's what I found most compelling
about Anthropica's approach to AI education.
Their team has said,
we would much rather teach a million people not to use AI
than watch a billion people
become dependent on this technology.
Read that again.
This isn't about using AI more.
It's about using it with intention on your terms
as a genuine thinker partner, not as a crutch.
The success criterion for AI fluency is beautifully simple.
Can you clearly articulate when you want to use the AI
and when you don't?
Not how many prompts you know,
not how many tools you've tried, just that.
The ability to make a conscious, intentional choice.
有意识、故意选择的能力。
So how do you build that capacity?
那么你如何建立这种能力？
Through the AI fluency frameworks,
通过AI流畅性框架，
a set of four interconnected competencies
一套四个相互关联的能力
known as the four Ds, delegation, description,
称为四个D：委派、描述、
discernment, and diligence.
辨别和勤奋。
Let's go through each one.
让我们逐一了解。
The first D is delegation.
第一个D是委派。
Delegation asks one fundamental question.
委派提出一个基本问题。
Who does what?
谁做什么？
In every interaction with AI,
在与AI的每次互动中，
you are making choice consciously or not
你都在有意识或无意识地做出选择，
about what role AI plays and what role you play.
关于AI扮演什么角色以及你扮演什么角色。
AI fluency means making that choice deliberately.
AI流畅性意味着故意做出这个选择。
There are three parts to delegation.
委派有三个部分。
The first one is go clarity.
第一部分是明确目标。
Before you open any AI tool,
在打开任何AI工具之前，
know what you're actually trying to achieve.
要知道你实际上想要实现什么。
Help me write an email is not a go.
“帮我写一封邮件”并不是一个明确的目标。
Draft a follow-up email to client
给客户起草一封跟进邮件，
who went silent after our proposal.
他在我们的提案后沉默不语。
Acknowledge the delay, briefly restate the value,
承认延迟，简要重申价值，
and end with a single low friction ask.
并以一个简单的低阻力请求结束。
That's a go.
这才是明确的目标。
The second is platform awareness.
第二部分是平台意识。
Different tools have different strengths.
不同的工具有不同的优势。
Claude is particularly strong at structural analysis,
Claude在结构分析、
nuanced writing, and complex reasoning.
细致写作和复杂推理方面特别强。
Knowing where to go for what kind of work
知道在什么工作中该使用什么工具，
is itself a skill.
本身就是一种技能。
And the last one, task distribution.
AI handles execution and pattern work.
You handle direction, judgment,
and relationship-sensitive decisions.
The second D is description,
how you communicate with AI.
This is where most people struggle,
which is exactly why they get mediocre results.
Here's the golden rule.
Vague input always produces vague output.
Great description uses what's called the three Ps.
The first P is product description.
Tell AI exactly what you want,
not just the topic, the format, the audience,
the tone, the length, be specific.
The second P is process description.
Tell AI how to approach the task.
Should it analyze multiple angles
or break the work into stages?
The third P is performance description.
Set expectations for the interaction itself.
Should AI ask clarifying questions,
challenging your assumptions?
Be brief or thorough.
Think of it as briefing a brilliant new colleague.
The better your brief, the better their work.
I want to spend a moment on this
because it's one of the most important principles
in AI fluency.
Vague input always produces vague output.
Most AI frustration,
大多数对人工智能的挫败感，
the sense that AI doesn't really get it,
源于对人工智能理解的怀疑，
traces back to this.
这可以追溯到这里。
It's not a limitation of the model,
这不是模型的局限，
it's a limitation of the description.
而是描述的局限。
The third D is discernment,
第三个D是辨别力，
and this is where AI fluency separates professionals
这就是人工智能流利度将专业人士
from casual users.
与普通用户区分开的地方。
AI sounds confident even when it's wrong.
人工智能即使错误也听起来很自信。
It states incorrect facts
它以与正确事实相同的语气
with the same tone as correct ones.
陈述不正确的事实。
It generates plausible sounding reasoning
它生成听起来合理的推理，
that doesn't quite hold together.
但并不完全成立。
The fourth P is trusting professional language.
第四个P是信任专业语言。
Discernment is the practice of reading AI outputs
辨别力是对人工智能输出的
with genuine critical evaluation.
真实批判性评估的实践。
There are three lenses.
有三个视角。
The first one is part of discernment.
第一个是辨别力的一部分。
Is this accurate?
这准确吗？
Is it logically coherent?
逻辑上连贯吗？
Is it appropriate for my purpose?
适合我的目的吗？
Do I have the domain knowledge to catch what might be wrong?
我是否拥有识别错误的领域知识？
The second is processed discernment.
第二个是处理后的辨别力。
Or just organizing information
或者只是将信息
into impressive looking structures.
组织成看起来令人印象深刻的结构。
Is that real thinking here?
这里是真正的思考吗？
Or confident noise?
还是自信的噪音？
Third one is performance discernment.
第三个是表现辨别力。
Did the response actually help me?
这个回应真的对我有帮助吗？
Does it match the tone I needed?
它符合我需要的语气吗？
Is it the right level of depth?
深度合适吗？
Here's the habit to build.
这是要培养的习惯。
Read every AI output as if a competitor wrote it.
把每个AI输出都当作竞争对手写的。
Skeptically, not looking for what's right,
持怀疑态度，而不是寻找正确的，
looking for what might be wrong.
寻找可能出错的地方。
The fourth D is diligence.
第四个D是勤奋。
And it comes down to one word, responsibility.
归结为一个词，责任。
No matter how good the AI output is,
无论AI输出多么优秀，
you are always responsible for what you put your name on.
你始终对自己署名的内容负责。
There are three parts.
分为三个部分。
The first part is creation diligence.
第一部分是创作勤奋。
Choose your AI tools deliberately.
故意选择你的AI工具。
If you're handling sensitive information,
如果你处理敏感信息，
are you sure that platform has appropriate data policies?
你确定那个平台有适当的数据政策吗？
The second is transparency diligence.
第二部分是透明度勤奋。
When the AI has played a significant role in your work,
当AI在你的工作中发挥了重要作用时，
be honest about that.
要诚实地说明这一点。
The third is deployment diligence.
第三部分是部署勤奋。
Before anything reaches another person,
在任何东西传递给其他人之前，
a professor, a client, a colleague,
教授、客户、同事，
it passes through your judgment.
都要经过你的判断。
AI's first draft is now the final product.
AI的初稿现在是最终产品。
You are the last line of quality control.
你是最后的质量控制线。
What's beautiful about this four D
这四个D的美妙之处在于，
is that they form a cycle, not a checklist.
它们形成一个循环，而不是一个清单。
You delegate, you describe,
你委派，你描述，
you discern, you practice diligence.
你辨别，你实践勤奋。
Then you loop back, smart delegation next time,
然后你再回头，下次智能委派，
sharper descriptions, more sophisticated discernment.
更精准的描述，更复杂的辨别。
This is what it means to grow as an AI-fluent practitioner,
这就是作为一个AI流利的从业者成长的意义。
not just doing tasks.
不仅仅是执行任务。
Let's bring this to life with a real example,
让我们用一个真实的例子来说明，
one that shows AI fluency at its most creative.
一个展示AI创造力的流畅性。
Imagine you're a writer collaborating with AI
想象你是一位与AI合作的作家，
to create character concepts for a story.
为一个故事创作角色概念。
You have a world, a plot, and a vision.
你有一个世界，一个情节和一个愿景。
Where does AI fit and where does it not?
AI适合什么，哪里又不适合？
Pause and think about it.
停下来想一想。
With delegation, you draw a deliberate line independently.
通过委托，你独立划定了一条明确的界限。
You develop the character's core, their deepest desires,
你发展角色的核心，他们最深的渴望，
their defining flaws, their backstory.
他们的缺陷，他们的背景故事。
These belong to you.
这些属于你。
They are the soul of the character.
它们是角色的灵魂。
Through AI collaboration, you explore personality,
通过与AI的合作，你探索个性，
appearance, how this character fits the story world,
外貌，这个角色如何融入故事世界，
and how they're engaged with others across later chapters.
以及他们在后面的章节中如何与他人互动。
The principle here is that humans define the soul
这里的原则是人类定义灵魂
and the core.
和核心。
AI exhausts the possibilities of vision,
AI耗尽了视觉、
detail, and collision.
细节和碰撞的可能性。
With description, you give AI the full story background,
通过描述，你向AI提供完整的故事背景，
the world's rules, its tensions, its history,
世界的规则、紧张关系、历史，
you specify what kinds of character this story needs
你具体说明这个故事需要什么样的角色，
and crucially, what it doesn't.
以及至关重要的，它不需要什么。
So every suggestion stays inside your creative vision.
因此，每个建议都保持在你的创意愿景之内。
You also establish cultural context,
你还建立文化背景，
naming conventions, the aesthetic register,
命名惯例，审美风格，
the emotional tone.
情感基调。
With discernment, you keep elements
通过洞察力，你保留了
that are essential to a key plot moment
对关键情节时刻至关重要的元素。
or that sharply illuminate a character's personality.
或是能清晰照亮角色个性的。
You modify whatever doesn't fit the world you've envisioned.
你修改任何不符合你设想的世界的东西。
And here's the most powerful discernment practice,
这是最强大的辨别练习，
deliberately discard AI's first two suggestions.
故意舍弃AI的前两个建议。
They'll almost always be the most predictable.
它们几乎总是最可预测的。
Go to the third or fourth idea.
去第三个或第四个想法。
That's where the unexpected adjustment decision leaves.
那是意外调整决策的来源。
With the diligence, every character that makes it
凭借努力，每个进入你故事的角色
into your story is yours to stand behind.
都是你可以支持的。
It can explain why they exist, what role they serve,
它可以解释他们为何存在，他们的角色，
and how they were shaped.
以及他们是如何形成的。
Hence, the most important thing I want you to take away.
因此，我希望你记住的最重要的事情。
AI fluency is not about becoming more like a machine.
AI流利度并不是变得更像机器。
It's about becoming more fully human.
而是变得更加人性化。
When you're fluent with AI,
当你与AI流利时，
your critical thinking doesn't diminish.
你的批判性思维不会减弱。
It gets sharper
反而会更加敏锐，
because you have a powerful thinking partner.
因为你有一个强大的思维伙伴。
Your judgment doesn't weaken.
你的判断力不会减弱。
It gets more refined.
反而会更加精炼。
Your creativity doesn't shrink.
你的创造力不会缩小。
It expands.
反而会扩展。
In a world where AI can generate endless content,
在一个AI可以生成无尽内容的世界里，
your ability to think critically, to discern,
你批判性思考的能力、辨别能力、
to take responsibility,
以及承担责任的能力，
those are your most valuable assets.
这些都是你最宝贵的资产。
So here's what I'd encourage you to do.
所以这是我鼓励你做的。
First, take Anthropic's free AI fluency course.
首先，参加Anthropic的免费AI流利度课程。
It's called AI Fluency Framework and Foundations.
它叫做AI流利度框架与基础。
It's free, it's rigorous, and it takes about an hour.
这是免费的，内容严谨，大约需要一个小时。
I'll link it below.
我会把链接放在下面。
Second, the next time you work with AI,
第二，下次你使用AI时，
go through the four Ds consciously.
要有意识地经历四个D。
Delegate intentionally, describe precisely,
有意委派，准确描述，
discern critically, and practice diligence.
批判性辨别，勤奋实践。
Third, share this with someone who needs to hear it
第三，把这个分享给需要听的人，
because AI fluency is a superpower
因为AI流利是一种超能力，
and it's one that everyone deserves access to.
每个人都应该拥有这种能力。
Remember, you're not just here to use AI.
记住，你不仅仅是来使用AI的。
You're here to work with it on your term.
你是来按照自己的方式与之合作的。